August 25th, 1991.
A 21-year-old graduate student in Helsinki
...named Linus Torvalds
...announces he's doing a free operating system.
Just a hobby.
Won't be a big professional thing.
Fast forward a few years later,
...and that hobby evolves into
...one of the most important projects
...in the history of computing.
Most operating systems were created
...to make shitloads of money.
STEVE BALLMER: "That's right!"
"It's 99 dollars!"
"It's an incredible value,"
"...but it's true!"
"It's Windows from Microsoft!"
"Order today!"
But Linux was a revolution
...based on a simple principle:
Software should be free and open.
Today, we'll take a look
...at the weird history of Linux,
...and in the process
...answer the question of
"Why are there so many Linux distros?"
But before we can even talk about Linux,
...we need to travel back to 1969.
While Grandpa was dropping acid at Woodstock,
...Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie
...were creating the Unix operating system.
Unix was well-loved
...by both businesses and universities.
There was one problem though.
The code was owned by AT&T.
And in 1977,
...when UC Berkeley created
...their own Berkeley software distribution,
...AT&T sued them.
That put limitations on Unix development
...and led to a period known as
...the 'Unix wars'.
A few years later in 1983,
...Richard Stallman creates
...the GNU Project,
...which was intended to be a
...free and open replacement for Unix.
But Unix was a big complex project
...with hundreds of different applications,
...and replacing it was no easy task.
Over the next few years,
...the project recreated many of the applications
...that you know and love today.
Tools that are often used synonymously with Linux
...like Tar,
...Bash,
...and Emacs,
...just to name a few.
By the early 90s,
...GNU had all this great software,
...but it was missing one essential component:
The operating system kernel.
A complete operating system
...needs a kernel to sit in between
...the hardware and the software,
...where it can allocate
...CPU and memory resources
...to run software applications.
Luckily, it was right around this time
...that Linus Torvalds was working on
...his hobby operating system.
Originally,
...it was going to be called
'Freax',
...because the name 'Linux'
...was too egotistical.
But as fate would have it,
...the admin for the FTP server at the time
...didn't like the name,
...and changed it without his consent,
...and the name stuck from there on out.
Initially,
...Linux was released
...with a proprietary license
...that had limitations on commercial use.
However,
...by the end of 1992,
...it was released under the
...GNU General Public License,
...and this gave birth
...to a complete operating system
...that we know today
...as 'GNU plus Linux'.
The following year,
...hundreds of developers
...jumped on the Linux project
...and started adapting it
...to the GNU environment.
The beauty of the Linux kernel
...is that it gave developers the ability
...to build custom operating systems
...that felt like Unix
...but didn't come with the fear
...of being sued down the road.
Ultimately,
...this led to some of the first Linux distributions
...like Softlanding,
...Yggdrasil,
...and Slackware.
But what is a Linux distro exactly?
A distro is a complete operating system
...based on the Linux kernel
...that contains a bunch of packages and libraries
...and typically a package manager
...to install additional applications,
...and possibly a Windows system
...if there's a GUI involved.
Many distros
...might share the same default user interface.
Popular UI options include
...GNOME,
...KDE's Plasma,
...MATE,
...Cinnamon,
...and a bunch of others.
Today, there's nearly
...a thousand different Linux distros out there,
...and they've all been customized
...to serve different purposes.
Some of them are designed
...for enterprise users,
...while others are for home users.
Some distros only run on servers,
...while others are designed for
...desktop,
...mobile,
...and embedded devices.
And each distro
...is usually backed by a community
...that has its own set of
...philosophical and technical opinions.
Most of these older distros
...are no longer maintained
...and just considered historical artifacts.
One exception is
...Slackware.
It had a release as recently as
...2016,
...and has spawned a bunch of different variations.
Most notably,
...it led to the openSUSE project,
...which remains a very popular
...general-purpose distro,
...and is usually associated with
...professional power users.
But the most significant distro
...to come out of 1993
...was Debian.
It was established by Ian Murdock,
...and its name comes from his name
...combined with his ex-wife's name,
...and its first official release
...came in 1996
...as version 1.1 (Buzz).
And since then,
...each release contains a code name
...with a 'Toy Story' character.
A few years later,
...it led to the creation of
...Advanced Package Tool,
...or APT,
...although it was originally developed
...under the code name 'Deity'.
The Debian community is huge,
...and it's a great distro today
...and very popular on servers,
...but can also be used
...as a general-purpose distro.
It's minimal and stable,
...which are traits that have allowed it to father
...a huge number of offspring distros.
Some of them are highly specialized,
...like Raspberry Pi OS
...or SteamOS,
...but by far the most popular child of Debian
...is Ubuntu,
...which was first released in 2004
...and is managed by a British company called
'Canonical'.
It follows a semi-annual release schedule,
...where each release
...is named after an animal
...and a word with the same letter,
...like 'Cosmic Cuttlefish'.
It's extremely beginner-friendly
...and was really one of the first distros
...to open up Linux
...to the mainstream home computer user.
In recent years, though,
...it's received a lot of hate from the Linux community
...for releasing closed-source software
...and also selling data to third-party companies.
In any case,
...it remains extremely popular,
...and it even has a variety of different flavours
...like Kubuntu,
...Zubuntu,
...and Lubuntu,
...which are their own distributions
...that offer slight variations on the original.
Like Kubuntu, for example,
...it's designed to be a great entry point
...if you're transitioning from
...Microsoft Windows to Linux.
In addition,
...Ubuntu has spawned many other variations
...like Linux Mint,
...Peppermint,
...and Pop! OS,
...just to name a few of the most popular options.
Debian has a huge family tree,
...but if we go back to 1994,
...there is another Linux distro
...that also has a huge family tree
...called 'Red Hat'.
It was created by Mark Ewing
...and is known for its focus on
...security and reliability
...for enterprise users.
Red Hat adopted a business model
...where they maintain an open-source operating system,
...then make money by selling consulting integration
...and add-on services
...to big enterprise clients.
Today, it generates
...billions of dollars in revenue,
...and was recently acquired by IBM
...for an 11-figure price tag.
Red Hat has given birth
...to a bunch of children,
...most of which are associated with enterprise work
...and use either the RPM or YUM package manager.
Popular descendants include
...RHEL,
...CentOS,
...and Fedora,
...which is not only great for enterprise servers
...but also works well as a personal workstation.
And it's even the distro of choice
...by Linus Torvalds himself.
Now, one thing that you'll notice about Linux distros
...is that many of them do a lot of stuff
...that you don't actually need,
...that takes up space on your hardware
...and ultimately makes your life more complex.
There are two Linux families
...that came out in the early 2000s
...that are focused on simplicity,
...performance,
...and minimalism.
Gentoo, with its Enoch distro,
...came out in 2000
...and Arch came out in 2002.
If you'd like to keep things simple,
...then you'll probably like
...the Arch family of Linux distros.
It has its own package manager
...called 'pacman',
...and has adopted a rolling release model.
Unlike Ubuntu,
...that has a new major release every 6 months,
...Arch releases small updates
...that can be continuously updated in the OS.
Arch is also the parent of
...Manjaro,
...which is one of the most popular distros of today.
In addition to all these families that we've looked at,
...there are many popular independent distros,
...like the extremely lightweight Alpine,
...Fire OS for Amazon devices,
...and Android,
...which is used by billions of people every day.
When you think of the Linux kernel
...like the engine in your car,
...it starts to answer the question of
"Why are there so many Linux distros?"
Some cars are designed to go fast,
...others for comfort.
Some are engineered for enterprise,
...and others are just for fun.
As a developer,
...Linux is like a free engine
...that you can use to build your own car.
That freedom,
...along with GNU
...and the greater open-source ecosystem,
...motivates people to try new things
...and to profit by creating
...innovation within that ecosystem.
People who are threatened by it
...call it 'communism',
...but in reality it's the polar opposite,
...and the free market at its finest.
Today,
...even Microsoft fully supports Linux
...through its WSL project.
I'm gonna go ahead and wrap things up there.
There's a lot of aspects of the Linux history
...and the histories of individual distros
...that we didn't cover,
...but hopefully this gives you a general idea
...of how Linux came into existence,
...and the evolution of Linux distros over time.
Oh, and there's
...one random thing I almost forgot.
Back in 2005,
...the source code for linux
...was managed under a version control system
...called 'BitKeeper',
...that was controversial though,
...because it's proprietary software.
So Linus Torvalds
...did what any legend would do
...and he created Git.
Before you go,
...make sure to like and subscribe,
...and stay tuned
...for a lot more Linux content on this channel.
Thanks for watching,
...and I will see you in the next one.